# 往这一摆
Place them like this
# 跟那个小算盘似的
and it looks just like an abacus
# 挂糖了
Pour the sugar over
# 薄薄的一层
to create a thin layer
# 糖是嘎嘣脆
and that crackling crispy sound
# 冰糖葫芦
Candied hawthorn
# 这个是网友盼了已久已久了
Our viewers have been waiting a long, long time for this one
# 这是刚才洗了一遍水
We’ve just washed it with water
# 咱们现在处理一下 加点盐
Now we will start to prepare it. First we add salt
# 把这脏东西都处理掉
This cleans away any remaining dirt
# 再加上底口有点盐度
and adds a bit of saltiness
# 这样它不腻口了
so it’s not too sweet
# 要想甜 加点盐
If you want it sweet, you’ve got to add salt
# 控下水
Drain the water
# 糖葫芦也是庙会上的
Candied hawthorn is something
# 不可缺少的一个美食
no temple fair can be without
# 这糖葫芦 又简单又不简单
It’s so simple yet so hard to get right
# 其实关键是炒糖
The key to it is in cooking the caramel
# 炒过了呢就苦了
Overcook it and it turns bitter
# 炒的不够呢 粘牙
Undercook it and it sticks to the teeth
# 你把这难度说的这么大
You make a big deal of how difficult this is
# 就说明自己的技术高超啊这意思
Are you trying to demonstrate how skilful you are?
# 在师父跟大爷面前
Next to Master and Da Ye…
# 还是心里
I still feel a little
# 还是有点那什么
You know…
# 不是 师父还是厉害
Master is still the best
# 下次让二伯做一个 那叫翻砂的
Next time we should get Er Bai to do that sugar coated dish
# 那个是我强项
That one’s my specialty
# 过去我老做翻砂芋头 老粤菜
In the past, I would always be making sugar coated taro  -  an old Cantonese dish
# 炒出来特别好吃 是吧
I can make that one real good  -  oh really?
# 下次您来一个吧
We’ll get you to do it next time then
# 糖葫芦串好了
The skewers are all ready to go now
# 往这一摆跟那小算盘似的
Place them like this and it looks just like an abacus
# 开始熬糖
Now we can start cooking the sugar
# 260克水
260g of water
# 300克白砂糖
300g of white sugar
# 水炒 纯水炒
We will be using water to cook the sugar, water and nothing else
# 这刚开始大火
It’s just been put on high heat
# 待会快好的时候开始就小火了
We let it heat up first and turn it back down to low when it’s almost ready
# 抹点油这上头
Rub some oil here
# 待会不容易粘上 不容易粘
to prevent the sugar from sticking later on
# 这时候咱们稍微加一点点盐
Now add a small pinch of salt
# 吃到嘴里它不腻
so it’s not overly sweet
# 这个原来小的时候来这么一串
Back when we were kids, you would count yourself lucky
# 算是好生活了 是吧大爷
just to eat even one of these  -  isn’t that right, Da Ye?
# 很奢侈了
Luxurious is what it’d be
# 小时候小孩没那么多零食
Back in our days, kids didn’t have that many snacks
# 炒这糖色待会儿会有三个步骤
When caramelising the sugar, there are three main steps
# 第一个步骤 就是冒白泡
The first step is let the bubbles form
# 你看这会儿的糖 这个泡是白的
Look at how the sugar is here, the bubbles are white
# 再炒一会 晾凉了以后
If you keep cooking, after it has cooled and dried
# 就可以做成翻砂了
you can use it as a sugar coating
# 炒糖色不能着急
When caramelising sugar it’s important not to rush, you’ve got to be patient with it
# 还是大火 慢慢炒
It’s still on high heat  -  let it continue to caramelise slowly
# 这会有点上色了
You can see it’s starting to get a bit of colour
# 大爷现在就可以翻砂了
Da Ye could use this as sugar coating when it’s at this stage
# 这时候就得转小火了
We turn the heat down to low
# 第二个步骤
The second step
# 这糖深黄色的时候
When the caramel has taken on a dark yellow colour
# 再炒一会就可以拔丝了
keep cooking a bit longer and it will be ready for use as a sugar glaze
# 拔丝就蘸糖葫芦没问题了
This glaze will have no problem sticking to the hawthorn
# 然后这稠度一下来 稀释了
When it has reached this consistency, the water starts to take on the sugar
# 花泡一下去就能拔丝了
Keep stirring for a while longer and it’ll be ready for use
# 把火关了啊
Turn the heat off
# 离火 离下来
and take it off the hob
# 这时候你看 这糖色
Have a look at this colour
# 这时候拔丝好 金黄色
You know it’s ready when you see this golden hue
# 稀了你看见没有 这就行了
See how clear it is now
# 这时候可以挂了啊 挂糖了
We can now start glazing
# 薄薄的一层
a thin layer like this
# 速度要快
You’ve got to move quick for this step
# 好 齐活
Alright! It’s all ready
# 冰糖葫芦
Candied hawthorn
# 剩下这糖 我加点水
With the leftover glaze, we add some water
# 这会儿就糖色了
and we’re left with some caramelised sugar
# 炖个肉啊 炖个排骨
This is good to braise meat with like spare ribs
# 一举两得了啊 好嘞
Two birds with one stone
# 师父尝尝
Master, have a taste
# 听声音
Listen to that sound
# 嘎嘣脆
It has that crackling crispy sound
# 慢点 别把核当冰糖咬了
Slow down there, you’re going to end up chewing on the core
# 大爷咱们小时候
When we were young
# 要吃这么一串糖葫芦过年了
If you wanted to eat this, we’d have to wait for Chinese New Year
# 一想40多年过去了大爷
Thinking about it now, it must be around 40 years now right Da Ye?
# 多少看见糖葫芦有点伤悲
How many of these have I seen since then? Makes me a bit sad
# 我有30年
Its been 30 years for me
# 没吃过糖葫芦了
since I last ate this
# 真像二伯说的
It’s just like Er Bai says
# 我们想起了儿时的记忆
When we think back to our childhood
# 鼓励的话 二伯也说了 我也说了
Alright, Er Bai and I have both said words of encouragement
# 再说一个不足的地儿
Now lets talk about ways we could improve this
# 我见人家蘸糖葫芦
I saw someone making this once
# 其实蘸我们这大理石板上
but they were using a marble board
# 一定要有一个什么厚一点的石头板
It’s best to use a thicker stone board
# 外边晾一下 给它冻一下
then if you dry the surface and freeze it
# 或者让它镇凉一点
or press something cold against it
# 你这个糖往上一浇 唰一流
When the glaze falls off it
# 正好冰花出来 更精彩
it freezes and creates beautiful ice crystals
# 然后还有一点不足大爷
and there’s still one last thing, Da Ye
# 说说说 抢答了
Go on， over to you
# 我跟你说做这个
When you making this dish
# 核必须得去
it’s best to remove the core
# 要不然你让我们吐核多难受啊
otherwise people have to keep spitting it out, not the best eating experience, you know?
# 这必须得改
You’re not wrong, it’s much better to do it that way
# 好 感谢师父 感谢大爷 好
Alright, thank you Master. Thank you Da Ye